Finding Aid for Arab Community Center for Economic and Social Services records.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Arab Community Center for Economic and Social Services records
1976-2009
1992-2005
Arab Community Center for Economic and Social Services.
0.75 linear feet
1 archived websites online
98121 Bd 2
Based in Dearborn, MI, the Arab Community Center for Economic and Social Services (ACCESS) works to provide services and assistance to new immigrants. They seek to establish a sense of community among Arab Americans and to provide a place to express traditions and pursue cultural activities. The collection includes a history of the organization and of the Arab-American community in Detroit, newsletters, annual reports, and information about many of the organization's activities.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Donated by Arab Community Center for Economic and Social Services (donor no. 7938 ) in several accessions beginning in 1991. Select publications have been donated at different times by Orchard Lake School (donor no. 7402 ), Karen Majewski (donor no. 10014 ), Mary Anne Stella (donor no. 10769, and Sally Howell (donor no. 10840 ).
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The collection is open without restriction
Founded by a group of volunteers in 1971 out of a storefront in Dearborn's impoverished south end, the Arab Community Center for Economic and Social Services (ACCESS) was created to assist the Arab immigrant population adapt to life in the United States. ACCESS offers English instruction and interpreters and seek to establish a sense of community among Arab Americans. In addition ACCESS provides a place to express traditions and pursue cultural activities.
As of 2016, ACCESS is the largest Arab American human services nonprofit in the United States. With eight locations and more than 100 programs serving metro Detroit, ACCESS offers a wide range of social, economic, health and educational services to a diverse population. Through initiatives like the Arab American National Museum (AANM), the National Network for Arab American Communities (NNAAC), ACCESS Growth Center, and the Center for Arab American Philanthropy (CAAP), ACCESS serves all Americans.
The ACCESS records encompass an array of items donated at different times and include historical information about ACCESS, announcements, programs, newsletters, reports, miscellaneous publications, and archived website.
Subjects:
Arab Community Center for Economic and Social Services.; Arab Americans--Michigan.; Communities--Services for--Michigan.; Immigrants--Services for--Michigan.; Muslims--Michigan.
Genre Terms:
Websites.
- ACCESS records
  The ACCESS records encompass an array of items donated at different times. The records include historical information about ACCESS, announcements and other materials that inform about activities and programs, anniversary banquet newsletters, annual reports, and miscellaneous publications. Also, contents of the archived website starting from 2010.
  - History, 1996 (Box 1)
  - Activities and programs, 1976; 1991-2005 (Box 1)
  - Anniversary banquet, 2001-2003 (Box 1)
  - Anniversary dinner, 1992-1997; 2008; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Annual reports, 1987-2009 (Box 1)
  - Arab Center, 1976 (Box 1)
  - Newsletters, 1982-2004 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous publications, undated (Box 1)
  - Archived snapshots of the website
  - Archives snapshots of the website
Related Materials
Researchers should note that the Bentley Historical Library holds the following collections:
Sally Howell papers
Barbara C. Aswad Papers